[Music]
I told you at the beginning of the class
that I started working on this material
partly because I was interested in why
people were so inclined to to go to any
lengths to protect their belief systems
I wanted to understand and I knew that
those were systems of value right that
the belief system is something that
enables you to ascribe value to things
so that so that you can act in the world
towards things and away from things
roughly speaking and I've already made a
case to you that belief systems regulate
people's own emotions but not not as a
consequence of decreasing their death
anxiety or anything like that or even
directly decreasing their their threat
sensitivity or uncertainty but more
specifically by helping them orient
themselves in the world so that what
they do matches what they want in the
social environment and it's an important
set of distinctions because the
emotional control that belief systems
allow is mediated by success in the
social environment that's the crucial
thing it's not it's not directly it's
not as if you're holding a belief system
and that's directly inhibiting somehow
your emotional response Civet II it's
more that you share you have a mode of
orienting yourself in the world so that
other people can understand what you're
up to so that you can cooperate and
compete with them without conflict and
the fact that you can do that without
conflict and maybe even with cooperation
that's what regulates your emotion so
it's not only the fact of the beliefs
belief system it's the fact that it's
shared with everyone else and so people
are willing to defend their belief
systems because they're defending the
territorial structure that enables them
to make sense of the world and then to
act out making sense of the world with
everyone else around them now then the
question arises what if two different
groups of people have different belief
systems what do you do in a situation
like that and one answer is you
capitulate another answer is that you
fight another answer might be that you
come to some consensus about how the
difference between those different
belief systems might be mediated so that
you can inhabit the same territory
without subordination or without
conflict but if you're going to come
together in an agreement you can't do
that simply by abandoning the belief
system because the belief system is what
Orient's you in the world and so the
negotiation is very tricky and because
of that it often ends up in
subordination or conflict another
question that might arise out of that
rat's nest of questions is if you have
belief system a and you have belief
system B and they're in conflict is
there any principles that you can use or
any guidelines you can use to take the
belief systems apart to understand what
might be of central value in either of
them are both so that if you do bring
them together or even if one supersedes
the other that there's some evidence
that they're predicated on principles
that are actually viable and of course
that brings up the question of what
constitutes viable principles and I got
interested in that more particular
question because when the Cold War was
raging there were two ideological
systems set up in the world roughly
speaking there were of course more but
we can simplify it for the sake of
argument down to two and one was
predicated on the communitarian
principles that were put forward by Marx
and the other was a consequence of
the well I would say Western
individualistic free-market capitalist
democracies roughly speaking and then
you might ask yourself well were those
only it was that only a difference of
opinion right because that's the central
question it was just a difference of
opinion if what's underneath it is
arbitrary then a it doesn't matter which
system wins roughly speaking B there's
no right and wrong in the discussion
right it's and that that would be
something that would be more akin to a
postmodern claim it's just Group a puts
forward their claims to power and Group
B puts form their claims to power and
they're both equally valid and well have
adder fundamentally because there's no
way of solving the problem but it struck
me that that I didn't think that we
should leap to that conclusion so
rapidly and so I started to investigate
I think I started to investigate the sub
structure of Western thought
not so much communist thought because I
thought of communism as an interloper on
the scene it was a system that wasn't
devised and formalized until the late
1900s late 1800s and I didn't see it as
part of what you might describe as
organic development there's no mythology
so to speak at the basis of of the
communist perspective and one of the
things that's very interesting is that
although those ideas were roundly
defeated by the end of the 20th century
they're making a comeback so rapidly
that it's almost unbelievable you know I
got an email from a medical student
yesterday at the University of Toronto
and now they're the course is that they
have to take the mandatory these are
social justice courses include modules
on equity and equity is equality of
outcome it they're pushing people are
having the equality of outcome notion
pushed on them in mandatory training in
universities everywhere again an equity
isn't equality of opportunity its
equality of outcome you know that was
the central dictum of the communist
states in the 20th century it's like
what the hell how how did we get back to
that again already so and the idea being
is if there isn't absolute equality of
outcome within an organization that the
thing is corrupt and needs to be
restructured from the bottom up and then
the question of course is who decides
that
outcomes are equal by what means and
with what groups because you can you can
produce an infinite number of groups of
people with equally validly in some
sense and you're never going to get
equality of outcome across the infinite
number of ways that you can parse up
society into groups it's not even
technically possible unless everyone has
nothing
so anyways these are obviously very
powerful ideas and the mere fact that
they killed a hundred million people
already or more in the 20th century
wasn't enough to put them to rest
anyways so back to the main theme is
there something this is the main
question is there something is there a
set of ideas that Western civilization
is predicated on that are more than just
bloody opinion that's the question
because if there isn't well then what do
you what do you do about that it's
arbitrary you're just holding it for no
reason whatsoever it could be a
different system there's no reason to
stick with it all of those things like
it takes the it takes the core out of it
when that was Nietzsche's claim right he
said you take the core metaphysical
presupposition out from underneath
western civilization or any civilization
for that matter and the whole thing
loosens shake ins
shakes and crumbles well for Nietzsche
the metaphysical presupposition was God
well and then the question of course
well what even does that mean and in on
one hand it means I suppose adherence to
a dogmatic set of beliefs but then you
might ask yourself well is there
something else that it means it means at
least the hypothesis of some
transcendent value it means at least
that so you know
Nietzsche announced the death of God and
so one of the consequences of that note
Dostoevsky was working on exactly the
same set of ideas and in crime and
punishment in particular which is a book
like it's a necessary book that's the
thing is there's a number of books that
were written in the last hundred and
twenty years that you really have to
read and crime and punishment is one of
them and
I think the Gulag Archipelago is another
and probably beyond good and evil is
another but you know Dostoyevsky and
Nietzsche were writing in parallel it's
remarkable how much their their lives
intertwined and Nietzsche knew more
about Dostoyevsky then then is generally
known there's been some recent
scholarship indicating that but in
Dostoyevsky's book crime and punishment
he has a his main character Raskolnikov
decides that he's going to commit a
murder and he has very good
justification for the murder and
Dostoyevsky is very good at this he he
puts his characters into very very
difficult moral situations and gives
them full justification for pursuing the
the
pursuing the pathway that they're
pursuing and so Raskolnikov he's broke
and starving he wants to go to law
school his sister's about to prostitute
herself ruff roughly speaking by
marrying a guy that that hates her that
she hates and that and he has contempt
for her at least acts in that manner
he's trying to rescue his mother as well
who's also in dire financial straits he
he goes to a pawn broker to pawn his
meagre position so that he can continue
to scrape by and she has this nice I
believe it's her niece that's not very
bright who she basically treats as a
slave and is horrible too and and so the
character the pawnbroker has this money
Raskolnikov is in dire need he thinks
look I'll just kill her because why the
hell not I'll take her money she's not
doing any good with it anyways I'll free
your niece who's just lurking as a slave
she's got all these other people tangled
up in her pawnbroker schemes all that'll
happen is the world will be a better
place and the only thing that's holding
me back is conventional moral cowardice
and you know Dostoyevsky has his
character in Crime and Punishment go
through days hours hours and days and
weeks of intense imagination about this
rationalization about this trying to
justify himself placing a male outside
placing himself outside the law so that
he can perpetrate this act and telling
himself with all the best nihilistic
arguments that the only possible thing
that could be holding him back is an an
arbitrary sense of indoctrinated
morality and so Dostoyevsky explores
that he does commit the murder and then
of course all hell breaks loose because
things don't necessarily turn out the
way that you want he gets away with it
however well he gets away with it
technically because no one knows he did
it but he doesn't get away with it in
relationship to his own conscience and
so that the rest of the book explores
that well Dostoyevsky I believe it was
in crime and punishment although he
makes the same point in many of his
books he makes a very fundamental point
and this is the kind of point that that
I think that people who haven't
investigated these matters down this
particularly little particular literary
and philosophical pathway never grapple
with dusty
Sookie said straightforwardly if there's
no God so if there's no higher value
let's say if there's no transcendent
value then you can do whatever you want
and that's the question that he's
investigating and you see this is why I
have such frustration say with people
like Sam Harris this sort of radical
atheists because they seem to think that
once human beings abandoned their their
grounding in the transcendent that the
the plausible way forward is with a kind
of purist rationality that automatically
attributes to other people equivalent
value it's like I just don't understand
that they believe that that's the
rational pathway what the hell is
irrational about me getting exactly what
I want from every one of you whenever I
want it at every possible second why is
that irrational and how possibly is that
more irrational than us cooperating so
we can both have a good time of it I
don't understand that
I mean it's as if the the psychopathic
tendency is irrational
there's nothing irrational about it it's
pure naked self-interest how is that
irrational I don't understand that where
where's the pathway from rationality to
to an egalitarian virtue why the hell
not every man for himself and the devil
take the hindmost it's a perfectly
coherent philosophy and it's actually
one that you can Institute in the world
with a fair bit of material success if
you want to do it so I don't understa
Dawkins and Harris I inhabit is so
intensely conditioned by mythological
presuppositions that they take for
granted the ethic that emerges out of
that as if it's just a given a rational
given and this of course precisely ditch
his observation as well as Dostoyevsky's
that's Nietzsche's observation you don't
get it the ethic that you think is
normative is a consequence of its of its
writ of its nesting inside this
tremendously lengthy history much of
which was expressed in mythological
formulation you wipe that out you don't
get to keep all the presuppositions and
just assume that they're rationally
axiomatic
they're the rationale to make a rational
argument you have to start with an
initial proposition
well the proposition that underlies
Western culture is that there's a
transcendent morality now you could say
that's a transcendent morality and Stan
she ated in the figure of God that's
fine you could even call that a
personification of the morality if you
want to if you if you don't want to move
into a metaphysical space I'm not
arguing for the existence of God I'm
arguing that the ethic that drives our
culture is predicated on the idea of God
and that you can't just take that idea
away and expect the thing to remain
intact midair without any foundational
support now you don't have to buy that
but if you're interested in the idea
then you can read Nietzsche because
that's what he was trying to sort out
and it wasn't only Nietzsche he came to
that conclusion because many people have
come to that conclusion but I think the
two who've outlined it most
spectacularly were Nietzsche and
Dostoevsky and each is an unbelievably
influential philosopher you know I don't
think there was any one that was more
influential during the entire course of
the 20th century accepting a very very
tiny handful of other people accepting
the scientists we won't bother with
their with their discussion you could
put Marx in that category you could put
Freud in that category partly but after
that the list starts to get a lot
thinner you know so maybe there's ten
people up in that level and Dostoyevsky
of course I think I mean if if you ever
if anybody ever prepares a list of the
top ten greatest literary figures in the
world he would be in the top ten list
you know I think he's perhaps second to
Shakespeare and maybe above Shakespeare
in my estimation so these aren't trivial
people we're talking about and they
weren't dealing with trivial issues well
so then the question might be what's at
the bottom of the idea of a transcendent
value and I want to wanted to approach
that staying out of the metaphysical
domain as much as possible because you
can claim anything you want from a
minute
physical perspective and that's a big
problem and so people will say well why
come up with a hypothesis of God for
example God could be anything there's a
satire the Flying Spaghetti Monster
right is a classic satirical
representation of a deity that the
Atheist types used to buttress their
arguments and fair enough you know as a
satirical idea it's pretty damn funny
but there's things about this that
aren't the least bit of music and the
thing that's not amusing is well what if
anything is our culture predicated on
okay so what happened well Nietzsche and
Dostoevsky put this forth this set of
propositions and out of Dostoyevsky's
line of thinking to some degree grew
Solzhenitsyn Solzhenitsyn documented the
absolute horrors of equity predicated
Soviet society you know and we don't
teach we don't learn about that right
this I don't understand is that what
happened in the 20th century on the
radical left end of the spectrum is not
well documented students don't learn
about it why the hell is that we learn
about World War two we learn about what
happened in the Holocaust and fair
enough we absolutely should but nobody
knows it's mystery to everyone when I
talk about what happened in the Soviet
Union and that's absolutely appalling
and that's to say nothing about what
happened in China which was equally
horrible the system didn't work it was
predicated on the wrong values unless
you think that that sort of thing means
worked you know because you have to
define that as well but it collapsed
under its own weight after it killed
tens of millions of people that doesn't
really instill R it's not like Russia
has recovered it doesn't seem to me like
that's a very good definition of worked
now whatever we're doing in the West
seems to work for all of its flaws and
the question is are we just deceiving
ourselves is it just arbitrary power
politics an opinion or is there
something at the bottom of it so when
Solzhenitsyn wrote The Gulag Archipelago
he believed that the Russians would have
to return to Orthodox Christianity to
find their pathway forward and that's of
course has made him into a reactionary
in the eyes of many of his critics but
that is perhaps what is happening in
Russia although it's very difficult
tell because Putin also seems to be
using his affiliation with the Orthodox
Christian Church as a means to
consolidate power
so the situation in Russia is unclear
but a religious revival if that's
happening in Russia and perhaps it isn't
but if it is happening is something that
unfolds over decades and even centuries
so it's not an easy thing to evaluate
when it first starts to happen but
Solzhenitsyn drew the same conclusions
that Dostoevsky did fundamentally I'm
not not in exactly the same way but very
very close he believed as far as I could
tell that unless people were willing to
adhere to some sort of transcendent
value that they had no protection
against pathological ideologies and no
protection against the murderous
impulses that came along with them and I
found his work in unbelievably I found
his right incredible powerful incredible
I don't know how you can read that book
and not draw that kind of conclusion I
think people who criticize soul
Janette's and have never read the damn
book because that book is like it's like
going into the ring with Muhammad Ali
and being pummeled to death for half an
hour you know you don't recover from it
that easily so then Jung branched off of
Nietzsche and so Nietzsche's idea was
that people would have to create their
own values roughly speaking and I think
that's where Nietzsche's is.we is his
weakest because it isn't obvious to me
that people can create their own values
and I think he fell into and I don't
want to be a casual critic of Nietzsche
because that's always dangerous given
that he probably had an IQ of 260 you
know I mean he was way the hell out
there in the stratosphere and just when
you think you've understood what he was
talking about you can be bloody well
sure that you didn't but it does seem to
me and he was running out of time he
died young you know and he was trying to
solve this problem in a rush I would say
and he hypothesized that people would
have to become Superman over men roughly
speaking in order to deal with the death
of God and that idea sort of branched
off into Nazi propaganda because that's
in some sense what the Nazis were trying
to do with their promotion of the of the
perfect Aryan you know now it's a
mystery it's a missile of media in my
estimation and it was partly because his
sister who is a perverse creature
um what would you say doctored his work
in such a way so that it was more easily
appropriated by the Nazis but there is
some danger in what he said too because
the question is well if you're going to
transform yourself into the into the
giver of values what stops you from
inflating yourself into something like a
demigod and just pronouncing what the
values are going to be so that's a
problem
you know you're gonna replace tradition
with yourself
well there's dangers in that because
there's nothing to keep you humble
that's that's the most appropriate
objection there's nothing to keep you
humble and those things can spiral out
of control very rapidly and they did say
in the case of Hitler I mean it's easy
to blame what happened in Germany on
Hitler but that's a that's a big mistake
because it was a dialogue between Hitler
and the German people right Hitler
didn't create himself
it was co-creation he said things people
listened and told him back what to say
and then he said them and they listened
and they told him back what to say and
it looped until he was the mouthpiece of
their darkest desires
now that's a that's a game he was
willing to play but you can't think
about that as it isn't like Hitler
created Nazi Germany Hitler and the
Germans co-created Nazi Germany you know
when a leader gives articulation to the
imagination of the population that's
what a leader does and you know you
could say that while Hitler maybe Hitler
filtered what the Germans were telling
him through a particular lens because he
had no shortage of resentment and desire
for revenge in his own heart you know
it's not like his life was a spectacular
success before he became a political
activist and he was brutalized very
badly in World War one and he didn't get
to pursue his primary dream which was to
be an art student in Vienna and he had
applied three times and got rejected all
three times and so he was bitter about
that he was basically living on the
streets after World War one it wasn't
the world's happiest person and I'm sure
he carried a fair bit of resentment in
his heart when he was in the trenches in
World War one in
experience that he had all of his
friends were killed by a mortar when he
had wandered off to go do something else
so you know it's hard to even imagine
what something like that would do to you
but I can tell you when you're the only
survivor out of 20 people that's also
going to give you an enhanced sense of
your own specialness because the
alternative is just to think about how
goddamn arbitrary the universe really is
so so Jung studied Nietzsche in in great
detail and he was particularly
interested because Jung had his finger
on the central problems all the time
right because he was a great
psychologist and he was listening to
what people said and he was a staggering
genius as well and so like Nietzsche or
Dostoevsky or Solzhenitsyn he was that
kind of prophetic type I would say and
he understood as well perhaps what was
wrong with Nietzsche's formulation the
idea that people could only create their
new their own values and that's what
would replace the lacking fountain the
foundation that was now lacking under
Western civilization itself and he came
to his conclusion I would say through
Freud because Freud started analyzing
parts of the human cognitive process and
content that people hadn't attended to
before in any in any great detail and
that was primarily dreams you know the
idea of dream analysis I suppose is one
of Freud's perhaps Freud's major
contribution to modern Western thought
the idea was there was something to
dreams and I suppose what but for I did
has said hey look isn't it strange we
have this whole other form of thought
that we engage in at night it and it
speaks in language that we don't really
understand and so what the hell is that
and you can say and many modern people
do dreams are of no significance or even
that they're random processes which is
an absurd proposition obviously because
they're by ferrell whatever they are
they're obviously not random so so
Freud's idea was that there was some
something in dreams that was informative
so that's as now he had a method for
described for extracting out from the
dream
what the dream purported to represent
and he outlined that in great detail in
the interpretation of dreams and if you
want to read one book by Freud I would
highly recommend that when it's a very
long book and it's very detailed but
Freud does an extraordinarily
comprehensive analysis of the way that
dreams work now he made the because
because he had brought a theoretical
framework to bear even on his
investigation into dream structure he
concluded that dreams were essentially
wish fulfillment and that's where Jung
and Freud disagreed he also believed
that the primary motivating factor of
human beings was sexual and now that's a
tougher one to toss aside because even
if you're a Darwinian rather than a
Freudian you're going to obviously
support the proposition that sexual
motivation among any living creature is
going to be one of the highest order
motivations because otherwise creatures
don't repre
so the question is is that is that the
ultimate source of motivation and in
some sense the answer to that has to be
yes well Freud wanted to make that in
some ways the sole source of motivation
and I'm oversimplifying and I hate to do
that in relationship to Freud because he
was not a simple-minded character Young
had a dream once if I remember correctly
that Freud and you were excavating a
basement and so Freud had outlined in
the Freud had already discovered the
basement let's say so that would be the
unconscious structure of the psyche and
Jung broke through into another basement
that was a multi-chambered place so many
many many rooms and I suppose what drove
Jung and Freud apart was Jung's
proposition that there was a hell of a
lot more going down going on down there
than had already met the eye and they
broke on the idea that the sexual
impulse was primary roughly speaking
they broke when Jung wrote a book called
symbols of transformation which is
actually there's there's three books
that I know of that are sort of like
maps of meaning one is symbols of
transformation one is a book by Eric
Newman called the origins and history of
consciousness and the third and the
third one while his maps of meaning
they're the same book they're just like
they're trying to saw
the same problem from three different
directions they're all attempts to
address the same problem and so symbols
of transformation was a book that Jung
wrote about the fantasies of a
schizophrenic American woman and he was
he was trying to relate her fantasies to
these old mythological ideas and Jung's
idea essentially and this is an idea
that was shared by people like Piaget so
we're not going to say that you and
Laura Freud just pulled this idea out of
the air was that the the birthplace of
myth mythology and literature for that
matter was the dream that that that they
share structural that they share they
they share what mode of information
presentation and it's a relatively
radical hypothesis but but given that
they both they both represent dreams
dreams and mythological representations
share an essentially narrative structure
and they use their literary like you
know I mean it's not so unreasonable to
notice that a dream at night is like the
movie that you play in your head and
it's not unreasonable to note as well
that the dreams that you have at night
bear a relationship to the daydreams
that you have during the day it's a form
of cognition it seems like an
involuntary form of cognition no and
that's a very strange thing so Jung
thought about the dream as nature
speaking of its own accord roughly
speaking and so his idea was well when
you when you sleep you dream but the
dream happens to you it's not something
that you create the way that and you
don't even think about creating it
because I might say well what are you
thinking about and you'll say I'm
thinking about whatever it is and you'll
take credit in some sense for thinking
that because it seems like a voluntary
activity but what happens at night is
that you think but you think
involuntarily and so what Jung would say
is that means that something is thinking
in you and that's a perfectly reasonable
way of looking at it and this is one of
the things that's uncanny about the
psychoanalysts is they they were willing
to take their observations to their
logical conclusion
there are things that think in you what
are those things and what are they
thinking and why are they thinking it
now if you do dream analysis and this is
a tricky thing because who's to say if
you're dam analysis is correct right
it's very difficult to understand that
if you if you do dream analysis with
someone you generally have them lay out
their dream and then you ask them when
they're going through the dream a second
time you lay out the dream and you can
kind of get a picture of it and then
they lay out their dream a second time
and as they go through it every time
they mention a detail or character you
ask them what that reminds them of and
the hypothesis is that the dream is
presenting an image or an idea that's
associated with a network of ideas and
that if you can expand on the network of
ideas as you go through the dream you
can elaborate on the dream you can
expand it upwards and you can start to
see what it might be attempting to put
forward now Freud's idea was that the
dream knew what it was doing but that
its content was being suppressed and
oppressed by an internal sensor so the
dream had to be sneaky about what it was
saying because it was going to deliver a
message that the person didn't want to
hear and that that was tied up with his
idea of repression but that's not Jung's
idea see Jung's idea was different he
said no no the dream is trying to tell
you what is trying to tell you as clear
as it can that's just the best it can do
and so you could think of the dream and
this is I believe the right way to think
about it the dream is the birthplace of
thought the same way that artists are
the birthplace of culture it's exactly
the same process it's that your mind is
groping outward to try to comprehend
what it has not yet comprehended and it
does that first by trying to map it on
to image and it's doing that in the
dream and it's somewhat incoherent and
and and well let's stick with incoherent
because it's not yet a full-fledged
thought it's the birthplace of thought
it's a fantasy about what might be and
then if you can grip the fantasy and
share it with other people then maybe
they can elaborate upon it and bring it
into being with more clarity than it
would be a
merely existed as the precursor of a
thought in your imagination now because
Jung's idea too was ok you think you
think in words where the hell do those
thoughts come from well they just spring
into my head well that's not much of an
answer they just what pop out of the
void is there some sort of precursor to
the development of the ideas is there a
developmental pathway so here's an image
this is the Buddha
there's calm water there's a lotus the
roots go all the way down to the bottom
of the lake it's dark down there the
roots are embedded in the dark substrata
at the bottom of the lake the plant
moves upwards towards the light that the
water gets lighter and lighter as you
move upward with the root the flower
manifests itself on the surface and the
buddha sits in the middle that's an
image about how ideas develop they come
out from the bottom of reality and they
push themselves up towards the light and
they blast forward and something emerges
as a consequence that's what that image
means and it's an image the gold Buddha
that's sitting in the middle of the
Lotus is an image of the perfect person
you could think about the gold Buddha
who sits in a triangle as exactly the
same thing that's the eye on the top of
the pyramid these are all the same ideas
there's and what's the idea that's
trying to burst forward how to be in the
world well what other idea would burst
forward because it's the only problem
that you really have right how should
you manifest yourself properly in the
world it's everyone's question it's the
ultimate question it's been the ultimate
question since the beginning of time and
we've been working out that idea forever
first of all merely by acting it out and
then by representing the actions and
then by representing the representations
and spiraling all that together so I
started looking developmentally I
thought okay maybe these idea have roots
and this was partly predicated on the
observation from Dostoyevsky and Neches
and and and so forth that there did seem
to be a necessary pattern in moral in in
morality there seemed to be a necessary
pattern it wasn't arbitrary it was a it
was a representation of the specific
mode of human being and it isn't some
that's just imposed on you by your
cultures not something that's just
learned its intrinsic in you and it's
manifest in the culture at the same time
and there's a dial and met and and
there's a dialogue between those two
things the culture in nature where both
where the idea is embedded trying to
make make make the proper articulation
of that spring forward in each
individual and that's only to say these
aren't these aren't radical propositions
your nature strives so that you can
manifest yourself properly in the world
culture strives to aid you in that
endeavor is that is there something
about that that's that's that's of
dubious validity what else would it be
doing working for your death hardly
working for your destruction well you
could see that maybe when culture
becomes pathologized but to the degree
that it's able to maintain itself across
long periods of time it obviously has to
be striving in some way for the mana for
your individual manifestation so that
you can survive and flourish so there's
a there's a there's a co-creation of the
human being going on through nature and
through culture and well and then
perhaps with your own with your own
voluntary will participating whatever
the hell that is something we don't
understand at all and are prone to
dismiss because of that so then I
learned about PHA and PHA had some very
interesting ideas and I think I've told
you already what Piaget was up to he
wasn't a developmental psychologist he
didn't even regard himself as a
psychologist he wanted to reconcile
science and religion that's what he was
doing through his entire bloody life
because it would drove him crazy when he
was in adolescent and he didn't think
that he would be able to survive unless
he could bring those two things together
so he's working on the same problem and
so one of the things that Piaget who was
very prone to observation he was an
ethologist of human beings that's a good
way of thinking about an ethologist is a
scientist who studies animals by
watching their behavior rather than
studying them under laboratory
conditions and he got very interested in
the spontaneous emergence of morality in
play of children that was so smart
that's so smart that idea that you know
when kids come together and unify
themselves towards a particular goal
so in play that a morality emerges out
of that and that that morality and I've
mentioned this before there's a morality
in game one there's a morality in game
two there's a morality in game three
what's common across all those morality
ziz a meta morality and so the meta
morality emerges from the particular
morality x' that are embedded in
particular cooperative situations we
could say cooperative and competitive
situations you can expand that out today
you can expand that out biologically to
some degree to the idea of the dominance
hierarchy right every social animal and
even many animals who aren't social are
embedded in a dominance hierarchy the
dominance hierarchy has a structure we
couldn't call it a dominance hierarchy
dominance hierarchy a b c d e thousands
of them across thousands of years you
extract out from all of them
what's central to all of them that's the
pyramid of value what's the what's the
question do you need answered about the
pyramid of value what's at the top
because that's the ideal that's the eye
at the top of the pyramid or the golden
buddha in the in the lotus it's the same
thing it's the same thing as the
crucifix paradoxically enough and that
has to do it has to do with something
like the voluntary acceptance and
therefore transcendence of suffering
it's something like that these are not
arbitrary ideas they're deeply that's my
case anyways they're deeply deeply
deeply rooted in biology and culture
they're they're as deeply rooted in
biology as the dominance hierarchy is
rooted in biology and we already know
the answer to that the dominance
hierarchies been around for 350 million
years it's a long time you don't get to
just brush that off and say well
morality some sort of second-order
cognitive problem it's like no it's not
I can't I can tell you something about
its instantiation in your nervous system
you have a counter at the bottom of your
brain that keeps track of where you are
in terms of your status and it bloody
well regulates the sensitivity of your
mo
so if you're at the bottom of the
hierarchy barely clinging on to the
world everything overwhelms you and
that's because you're damn near dead and
so everything should overwhelm you
you've got no extra resources any more
threat you're sunk so you become
extremely sensitive to negative emotion
and maybe also impulsive so that you
grab well the grabbing is good and if
you're near the top in the dominance
hierarchy and your counter tells you
that then your serotonin levels go up
you're less sensitive to negative
emotion you're less impulsive you live
longer like everything works in your
favor your immune system functions
better and you're oriented at least to
some degree towards the medium and long
term future and you can afford that
because all hell isn't breaking loose
around you all the time and so then the
question is is there a way of being that
increases the probability that you're
going to move up dominance hierarchies
well that doesn't seem to be a
particularly provocative proposition
unless you think that it's completely
arbitrary and random and that you can
think that if you want but I don't think
there's any evidence for that whatsoever
I mean we certainly have even for sexual
selection we impose criteria they're not
rammed random and arbitrary so okay so
back to young so what was young trying
to do well he was trying to see see
young believed that once we had stopped
populating the cosmos with gods that
they went inside that's a good way of
thinking well think think about it this
way you know mm-hmm an archaic person
looks at the sky and uses his
imagination to populate the sky
what's the sky well it's the
constellations it's the domain of the
gods well why well because the gods are
what RB are out there beyond your
understanding well that's what you see
when you look up at the sky so you
populate the night sky
with figures of your imagination so the
gods are the things that you broadcast
out of your imagination and see spread
over the world it's like the contents of
your unconscious are manifesting
themselves when you encounter the
unknown it's exactly what it is that's
how how else could it be right you're
projecting your fantasy onto what you
don't understand that's how you start to
cope with what you don't understand you
populate the unknown with deities where
did they come from they came from your
imagination well what happens when you
take them out of the world do they
disappear
no they just go back into your
imagination so that's where young dug
down to find them that's the same motif
as rescuing your dead father from
the-from or rescuing your father from
the belly of the whale it's the same
idea is that the corpses of the gods
inhabit your imagination so where do you
go if you need to revivify them you go
into your imagination and that's exactly
what Jung did and that mean it this is
no secret if you read Jung he tells you
that's what he did he tells you that's
why he did it it's not an interpretation
on my part well so then then the
question is what's down there is it just
mass and catastrophe or is there
something in it that's patterned well
Jung's
proposition was that Yuri did you really
discover the great archetypes that guide
human being by investigating the
structure of your imagination when he
thought about the imagination in some
sense at least in part as a
manifestation of your of your biology
well yes
what else would it be you know when I
told you that story about my nephew I
believe right about him running around
as a knight and then going off to have a
combat with the dwarves and the Dragons
it's like well where did that come from
well partly it came from his culture
right because if he was a knight and and
so obviously that's a cultural construct
but the thing is is that his imagination
is it's this structure that's looking
for things to fill itself with just like
your predisposition to language you have
a predisposition to language what is
that we don't know what does it do
it looks for things in the world to fill
itself with right and if you're if you
first of all wouldn't you start to learn
how to speak you babble every phoneme
did you know that there's there's lot
there's if I was learning to speak an
Asian language there would be phonemes I
couldn't pronounce and vice-versa an
infant all of
they babble all the phonemes and then as
they start to learn the language they
lose the ability to say a bunch of them
and only retain the ones that are
relevant to that language so a baby
babbles all laying all possible
languages that's a way of thinking about
it and then loses the ability so that's
a man if that's you can see there so you
could say well you manifest the
potential to be possessed by all the set
of all possible archetypes it's built
into your biology and then as your
enculturated in your own culture the set
of archetypes that manifest its manifest
themselves in that culture are the ones
that you pull in for your own use so my
my nephew's running around like a knight
well you know if he would have been born
in the middle of the Amazon he would be
running around with a bow and you know a
poisoned arrow and a bow it's the same
thing it's the same idea it's just
trapped out in different cultural dress
and he his little imagination was trying
to solve the problem how do you deal
with the unknown well what's the unknown
it's these little devils that keep
biting jumping up on you and biting you
and they come out without end
so just killing them it's like cutting
the head off the Hydra right seven more
grow well what the hell good is it to
solve one problem when there's just a
bunch more problems that are come gonna
come after you and that's everyone's
question that's the ultimate question of
nihilism right
why bother solving a problem if all
that's going to happen is that twenty
more problems are going to come your way
why not just give up and die well right
it's a good question it's that it's a
good question right is this suffering so
intense that the whole game should just
be brought to an end
that's another fundamental question of
existence and people who've become truly
malevolent answer that question in the
affirmative they say it's too much we
should destroy it
now I wouldn't say they're precisely
doing it only for humanitarian reasons
but you have to understand and
appreciate the logic it's not irrational
that's the other thing it's not
irrational to work for the destruction
of being it's not irrational in fact it
might be the most
rational thing you could come up with
depends on your initial initial set of
presuppositions so you down into the
belly of the beast so to speak to to to
to to see what lurks in the imagination
he sees the birthplace of archetypal
ideas well what are archetypal ideas
there there are patterns of it you could
think about them as as representations
of patterns of adaptive behavior and so
then you might ask well where did they
come from well that's part of what I've
been trying to to to teach you about
they evolved as far as I can tell right
they evolved collectively is that our
society and this is the dominance
hierarchy idea doormen desire key set
themselves up as a matter of course
they're the standard way that animals
organize themselves in a territory well
ok human beings are watching those
dominance hierarchies since we became
self-aware thinking what the hell are we
up to what the hell are we up to what's
and and there's a question that lurks in
there what constitutes acceptable power
what constitutes acceptable sovereignty
who should lead who should rule what
should be at the top well we talked
about that the Mesopotamians figured
that out speech and vision that's Marduk
speech vision and the willingness to
confront the terrible unknown that's
what should rule well what's that an
arbitrary idea or is that a great idea
how could it be any other way well
that's what human beings are like and I
don't think that you can read the
Mesopotamian story and understand the
reference which isn't an easy thing to
do and fail to draw that conclusion
Marduk has eyes all the way around his
head he speaks magic words he goes off
to fight timeout the dragon of chaos
well what's that that's the reptilian
predator that lurks in the unknown well
is any of that is there anything about
any of that that stands in opposition to
what you would presume if you were just
analyzing our situation from a purely
biological perspective we're prey
animals were predators we'd be
threatened by reptiles forever
why
wouldn't we use the predator that lurks
in the dark forest or the water as a
representative of the unknown why
wouldn't we harness that circuitry we
already have it at hand and even more to
the point how could we do anything else
it's it makes perfect sense well so then
what you might say well what would you
want to be king
you could say king of the world or king
of your own soul what do you want to
subordinate yourself to how about your
heroic willingness to encounter the
unknown and articulate it and share that
with people
there's no nobler vision than that and I
don't see that it's merely arbitrary and
so and it's not merely arbitrary -
because if you do that to the degree
that you do that assuming your society
isn't entirely corrupt you will be
successful it will actually aid you
practically you'll rise up above men
you'll be selected by women
you'll be admirable you'll be valued and
and you know that because if you look at
the people that you admire and value
again unless you've taken a detour into
dark places and are possessed with
admiration for people who are working
for malevolent purposes and for
destruction you just have to watch the
people that you admire and try to figure
out what's common across them and draw
your own conclusions and you can ask
yourself - when you're torturing
yourself with your conscience because
you're not doing what you should be and
you know it
what is it that you're torturing
yourself in relationship to you have a
vision of your own ideal and you torment
yourself if you're not matching it
what's the ideal well you don't know
right it's it's kind of incoherent and
and poorly articulated but that doesn't
mean it isn't trying to manifest itself
and and make itself known to you it's
really the purpose of religious
education is to make that ideal
articulated well we've lost that it's
not a good thing okay so I talked to you
about the Mesopotamian story and I
talked to you about the Egyptian story
and what I thought it meant and it's a
bit of an elaboration on the same theme
because it says well the hero isn't only
the the deity
transcendant pattern let's say that goes
out into the unknown cuts it into pieces
and makes the world that's not good
enough because it only deals with the
terrible mother that's one way of
thinking about it but there's a terrible
father too once culture gets
instantiated in in in large scale and
the Egyptians had that problem too
problems chaos second problem
pathological order well structures tend
towards pathological order the Egyptians
laid out why that Seth right Seth is the
evil advisor of the king who's lurking
in the background all the time trying to
tear the structure down for his own
malevolent purposes so now and then that
overcomes the structure and destroys the
and and what rigidify Xand makes
malevolent the entire social structures
so it degenerates and to say fascist
totalitarianism something like that and
that's being a threat since we've had
highly organized societies then the hero
ends up in the underworld and has to
come back and and do direct combat with
that malevolent force at the price of
his own consciousness right because the
Horus gets one of his eyes destroyed
it's no bloody joke to face the forces
that make a culture rigid and malevolent
so there's an addition to the hero
archetype two things happen one you go
out and you conquer chaos and you make
order out of it but the second is you
take pathological order recast it into
chaos and then allow it to reemerge and
you do that not in some arbitrary sense
but in tandem with your rescued father
and that's I guess in part what
Nietzsche Mik missed as far as I can
tell is he didn't he knew that he knew
of the death of God perhaps he didn't
know that it had happened many times
Myrcella had documented that across many
cultures but what Nietzsche didn't seem
to lay out at least in his vision of the
Superman or the over man was that it was
a responsibility of the person who wants
to revivify the culture to go down and
rescue the damn culture which is what
you're supposed to be doing in
university because your father is lying
dead in the libraries right so you're
supposed to be going in there and taking
that spirit out of the books and
manifesting it in your own being that's
what the university's
were for although I don't think that's
what they're for anymore so we talked
about the Mesopotamians story and we
talked about the Egyptian story and
other people have documented the
emergence of hero mythology in cultures
far more diverse than the ones that I'm
exposing you to that was done most
popularly by Joseph Campbell but
Campbell's like I don't think Campbell
had a single idea that he didn't derive
from Jung and I'm not saying that in a
in a critical manner because Campbell
was good at standing as a mediator
between Union and a more general
population he did and that's that's a
non-trivial accomplishment seriously but
but but Jung is still the source of
those ideas and if you're serious about
them that's the person that you have to
go to for that kind of knowledge so now
I wanted to tell you some other stories
that are that are in some sense closer
to Western culture they're the stories
upon which Western cultures actually
predicated so I'm going to tell you well
I'm not only Western story today I'm
going to tell you a couple of stories
from Genesis and I'm going to tell you
about the story of the Buddha I'm going
to do that at the same time because the
story of the Buddha is almost a perfect
parallel structurally speaking to the
story of Adam and Eve and so I want to
show you that we can you can decide for
yourself if I'm imposing a pattern on it
because god only knows right or whether
or not once you have the key to
understanding the stories which I hope I
provided you with with the you know the
idea of the dragon of chaos and the
great mother and the great father in the
individual it gives you a schema that
you can use to understand the
characterizations of great stories and
as far as I can tell it works pretty
much universally across stories so so I
want to read I want to walk you through
those foundational stories and I would
say one of the things to know about the
way the Bible is structured there's a
couple of things you want to know about
it is that it was authored by multiple
people across extraordinarily vast spans
of time and then aggregated by other
people and sorted into something that
seemed to make sense and so you can
really think about it as a because Bible
is is a library it's
library of books it's not a book the
library is organized a certain way that
makes a kind of sense but it's not
exactly as if anyone decided what that
sense would be it's the collaborative
work of hundreds and thousands of people
across thousands of years attempting to
organize a collective story into
something that something out of which
the sense emerges it's like human beings
acted and then they dream dreamed about
how they acted and then they wrote down
what they dreamed about how they acted
and then they organized what they wrote
about how they dreamed they acted and
that's how that book came into being and
the information that's within it emerged
from the behavioral level upward right
rather than being imposed top down no
there's a there's a feedback right
because if you understand how you act
and that changes how you act and so you
can't you can't avoid the top-down
feedback but a tremendous amount of the
information in there and this is why
it's revelatory information we don't
know it's in there because how we act is
informative and then if you represent
how we act that's informative but the
information came from how we act not
from the representation of how we act
and then you might think well how did we
learn how to act and the answer is we've
been trying to figure out how to do that
for 3.5 billion years there's a lots of
information encoded in our actions and
in our social interactions way more than
we understand so we're acting something
out we don't understand what it is but
we're doing our best to pull that
information upward partly by dreaming
about it that's what you're doing at
night you're trying to figure out what
the hell you're up to well you don't
know because you don't know yourself in
totality how could you possibly know
best you can do is dream yourself up and
then speak yourself into some sort of
articulated existence it's just an
approximation because you who whatever
you is whatever you are rapidly
supersedes whatever you think you are
that's why people constantly shock
themselves you know if you were only
what you thought of yourself all
wouldn't life be simple you'd know
exactly what you were doing all the time
and you could
even control your own behavior well good
luck with that you can't do that for
yourself much less for other people so
let's go through these stories so
they're sequenced people are trying to
make sense out of them they're
aggregating these stories from all sorts
of different places all sorts of
different tribes all sorts of different
times and then trying to make them
coherent without losing the content and
without doing arbitrary editing and so
part of the reason that the Bible is
full of internal contradictions it's for
the same reason that a dream is full of
internal contradictions is if you impose
too much coherence on it you start
losing the look imagine you have an
imagine that you have a impressionist
painting
well it's messy and and and the the
image emerges and you might say well we
could replace that with a nice clean
line drawing or even a sequence of stick
figures and get the basic point across
it's like well you would but you'd lose
the the richness the unarticulated be
lost in the premature attempt to bring
logical closure to the phenomena and so
in fact we know already that that's
maybe the difference between dreams and
waking thought so waking thoughts
sacrifices completeness for coherence
right so whereas dream thought
sacrifices coherence for completeness
and that's that's that's not something
I'm saying arbitrarily this is something
that has been thought through by people
who've been thinking this sort of thing
through for a long time precise thought
excludes too much an imprecise thought
is not sufficiently coherent so we do
both precise thought left-hemisphere
linguistically mediate it's sequential
logical incoherent but complete thought
imagistic emotion based right hemisphere
the right hemisphere even has a more
diffuse structure it's like the right
hemisphere is trying to get a picture of
everything now it's not going to be a
very detailed picture because it's a
picture of everything
of contradictions but at least it's a
picture of everything and the left says
that's not good enough for precise
action and it's not so we'll narrow that
to precision but we lose the richness
but you need both so there's an
interplay well the documents that the
Bible is composed of are half dream and
half articulated thought and they have
the advantages of articulated thought
and the advantages of the dream but also
the disadvantages of both so it's a the
to the degree that it's articulated it's
in a dogmatic box to the degree that
it's a dream it's still incoherent but
it's the problem is you have to you have
to move through the entire world even
though you don't know it in detail so
you need detailed knowledge where
detailed knowledge is necessary and you
need vague but complete knowledge where
that's necessary it's an it's a very
uncomfortable balance but we have to
face everything even though we don't
understand anything completely now
Genesis the first stories in Genesis are
what would you say unn unn identifiably
ancient god only knows how old they are
and the story of noah here's an
interesting thing I know this guy who's
a he's a quak quak quak tribal member
and an artist who lives on the tip of
northern of Vancouver Island and the
culture he comes from is about fourteen
thousand years old something like that
and maybe it's not being unbroken for
fourteen thousand years very long period
of time and he he's not literate this
guy although he's very intelligent has a
great memory and is also a great artist
and he's told me some of the stories
that that have come down through the
quark Wacka Wacka tradition and he was
educated by his grandparents who were
original language speakers and he's an
original language speakers there are
many people like that left to think
there's only 3,000 in his particular
tribal group they have a story that's
the flood story that this except it's
canoes and it isn't a dove it's a crow
but the damn story is exactly the same
it's like well what the hell is up with
that in fact at the end it's not a canoe
it's a bunch of canoe
that are tied together and at the end
the canoes all break apart and that's
why there are people all over the world
it's like the story of the Tower of
Babel which I'm going to talk to you
about today it's so the reason I'm
telling you that is because the stories
at the beginning of Genesis are
extraordinarily old now so maybe he
tells the same story that we tell you
know making the presumption that we are
the people who who are part of this
judeo-christian tradition and I know
that that's not the case for everyone
either he's telling the same damn story
and it emerged from a central point so
long ago that it's 20,000 years or
30,000 years or maybe 50,000 years since
we moved out of Africa something like
that and this story has survived which
is certainly possible because oral do
you think can an oral traditions survive
that long that's the wrong question oral
traditions always survived that long
what's radical is that they disappear
were the radicals the oral tradition is
something that stays the same generation
after generation so how much innovation
do you think there isn't a small tribal
group none that's why they don't have
advanced technologies they stay the same
the stories stay the same so the idea
that they can be transmitted unchanged
over thousands and tens of thousands of
years is really not a debatable
proposition it's the norm so either the
stories emerge from a central source and
have never been lost so that you can
pick them up everywhere or there's
something about the stories that
automatically regenerates themselves and
I suppose it's a little bit of column a
and a little bit of column B it's like
my my nephew when he perceived himself
as a dragon slaying Knight it's like
well was that the continuation of an
oral tradition or was it something that
he spontaneously come up with and the
answer is both
both the pattern was there he just had
to see it and he saw it and synthesized
it and and encapsulated it in his own
imagination well that's not much
different than the oral tradition being
unbroken it's it's just a variant of the
same thing
I mean if you lose a story but everyone
acts it out you can reconstruct the
story right and if everyone doesn't act
it out then the culture dies because
there's some things about the story that
you have to act out if your culture is
going to survive that's the hypothesis
and then that would be well that would
be where you would search for ultimate
values the stories that enable you as an
individual to flourish in such a manner
that your culture flourishes in a way to
enhance your flourishing right that's
the right way that you want to organize
things you know that's what you do
inside a family if it's functioning well
right the family functions so that every
individual benefits from being in the
family and that strengthens the family
that's what Piaget called an
equilibrated solution technically
speaking when he was looking for the
origin of moral ideas he came up with
the idea of equilibrate equilibrate 'add
state and then equilibrated state is one
the three of you are in an equilibrated
state if you all want to be in that
state and while you're in that state the
things that you're doing together work
better and they facilitate each of your
development right so it's the stacking
of an ethical of a set of ethical
propositions so that the individual
benefits at the same time as the group
and you could you can increase that
stacking we could say well it's not only
that you want to organize yourself so
that all three of you get what you want
better than you would if you were alone
and so that you're healthy and so the
stacking also occurs all the way down
the physiological chain you want to be
manifesting yourself in the world so
that you remain as physiologically
healthy as you possibly can so your
stress responses are properly balanced
and all of that and then maybe your
equilibrate at state is well enough
developed so it doesn't just include the
three of you it extends outward beyond
you into the greater community and
things stack like that and that's is
they get if they all get stacked up
every level it's stacked on top of each
other properly you have an equilibrated
state and I don't think that that's any
different than a vision of paradise I
think those are the same thing so now
the question is well can that happen
that's a whole different story
I mean it happens in
your own life at those times where
everything comes together for you you
know it's chaotic and then everything
snaps together and you think that's
exactly right and it's unstable you
can't maintain it it fragments again but
that's what you're that's what you're
working towards if you have any sense
you're working towards that constantly
and I think that's what music represents
it's this stacking of harmonious
patterns right that are playing
themselves out and being and you watch
how people respond to music the
orchestra's led by the leader every
different individual plays his or her
part they're organized into string
sections and horn sections and so on so
you get individual sub group group
orchestra leader then maybe you have
people dancing well so what does that
mean so maybe it's men and women dancing
in front of that like a Viennese Waltz
so it's the the harmonious stacking of
pattern being in the background led by
someone who's making sure that the time
is in order and men and women arranging
themselves according to the patterns
right and everyone has a wonderful time
when that's happening and it's acting
out it's acting out the proposition that
all of these levels of being can be
stacked up harmoniously at the same time
everybody has a tremendously fun time
while they're doing it
maybe that's how you find a mate how to
dance and for exactly the same reason
it's an optimal place to do that you see
if there's someone that you can be with
with whom you can mutually act out the
patterns of being well we're all acting
that out at a dance we don't know what
we're doing we're having a good time
well yeah that's a little glimpse of
paradise that's what that good time is
now the Bible stories before what
happens what seems to happen is that you
can there's there's two cataclysmic
events that the first part of at the end
of the first part of Genesis
there's the flood so the prehistoric
world is wiped out by the flood and so
the idea there in some sense there's a
bunch of ideas but one of them is
there's a place in history past which we
cannot look and that's absolutely true
one of the things that's very strange
about human beings is that are written
civilizations the ones we have records
have all seemed to have popped up
somewhere in the neighborhood of five to
six thousand years ago it doesn't matter
where you look right
Central America China India Greece Egypt
it's all the same 6,000 years ago poof
there we were
well what happened before that well the
answer is we don't know everything is
obscured by the chaos of history before
that point and all that seemed urged out
of it so to speak are these incredibly
ancient stories and so we're gonna walk
through the ancient stories and see what
we can pull out of them we've already
done that with several so so there are
some representations of the Garden of
Eden so this is by Hieronymus Bosch I
don't know if you know who Hieronymus
Bosch is but he's definitely worth
looking up because he was one strange
character he was like I think he painted
in the 15th century if I remember
correctly he was like this 15th century
version of Salvador deli his paintings
are so uncanny that that they're still
shocking to the modern eye which is
really something because it's not easy
to shock a modern person with a visual
image but Hieronymous Bosch will
definitely do that and that's his
representation of paradise there's some
central structure in the middle that's
partly phallic and partly chambered so
and there's Adam and Eve you know United
by God so and there's one by peter paul
rubens and it's sort of the primordial
lush landscape that you might think
about as the what the ancestral human
home it's something like that a treed
landscape well white trees well we like
fruit we lived in trees why not trees I
mean even modern people have very
powerful tendency to think about trees
as sacred you wouldn't get
environmentalists tying themselves to
great
you know Douglas firs and protecting
them if there wasn't some deep felt
sense within us that they're sacred
whatever that means well trees are our
home well that's as close to sacred as
you're gonna get so ok so I'm going to
read you something from the book of Job
and this is God harassing job so I don't
know if you know the story of job but
it's a very interesting story and
basically what happens with job is that
God and the devil have a bat which seems
a little you know on the unreasonable
side for God but
he gets to do whatever he wants so he
hasn't bet with Satan roughly speaking
and says he says well job
he tells Satan that job is a good guy
and that he's faithful to God and Satan
says yeah let me let me out him for a
while I betcha we can do something about
that and God says roughly speaking no
you could touch him all you want he's
gonna stay faithful and and and Satan
says well we'll have a bet on that and
so God hands him over and what happens
to job it's like everything terrible
that you can imagine then happens to job
right his his all his family dies all
his possessions are destroyed he gets a
horrible skin disease and so then he's
sitting there by the fire sort of
scraping himself with bits of broken
pots and all his friends come around and
tell him that the reason all this
happened to him was because he deserved
it
so it's perfect right it's it's it's
it's like an ultimate suffering story
it's a precursor to the idea of the
crucifix that's one way of thinking
about it so and Joe has a chat with God
and asked some like Cain did roughly
what's going on and God attempts to he's
irritated that job would even dare to
question him it's like he's God it gets
to do whatever he wants it's a very
strange book anyways this is one of the
things that God says to job well God is
trying to justify himself I would say to
job and it's the reason I'm telling you
this you see is because so imagine that
you're trying to analyze a literary work
you might say well where's the meaning
in the literary work and the answer is
it's in the words word by word it's in
the phrases it's in the sentences it's
in the relationship of the sentences to
each other it's in the relationship of
the sentences within paragraphs it's in
the relationship of the paragraphs
within the contexts of the chapters and
it's in the relationship between the
chapters and the whole book and then the
book in the whole culture so you can't
it's not easy to localize the meaning it
exists at all those levels
simultaneously and they all inform one
another and what that means and it's
even worse in a book like the Bible I
want to show you a picture this is an
amazing picture
so let me tell you what this is so the
Bible is the world's first hyperlinked
document that's a good way of thinking
about it so what you have here so what
you see at the bottom there's a line
along the bottom and then there's small
lines coming down from it okay each of
those the line has dots on at each jot
is a is a verse okay and then there's a
line associated with the verse that's a
varying length and the length
corresponds to how many times that verse
is cross-reference somewhere else in the
document and then these rainbow-colored
lines are the cross references so now
that's really worth thinking about so
then you think well that book is deep
well why is it deep well it's because
every single thing in it refers to every
other thing it's connected like your
brain is connected like it's not a
linear document and the really the thing
is a book is a very strange thing right
because when you or even a story because
when you lay out the story in some sense
you're like god you're outside of the
space and time of the story
and so you can adjust the end to make
the beginning different you know how if
you watch a movie and then it's got a
surprise ending it changes the beginning
you thought the beginning was one thing
but it isn't it's something else well
when you lay out a story you can fiddle
with the story anywhere in the story and
so and you can also make something that
happens before dependent on something
that happens after which is very strange
and that's what's happened with the
Bible because people have worked on it
worked on it worked on it worked on it
trying to synthesize it and make it
coherent and make it make sense and so
they're continually connecting
everything that's inside of it to
everything else and so you end up with a
document map that looks like that so now
so you think about that everything is
connected to everything in that document
not chaotically but meaningfully just
like your brain is connected in a
meaningful way it's not everything isn't
connected to everything it's connected
in a meaningful way and then you think
well where what do the stories mean and
then the answer is well that's a hard
question because all of them are
connected with each other and then
there's all these different levels of
analysis and so you can pull out
meanings at one level of analysis that
aren't self-evident at another
level of analysis just like if you're
listening to a complex piece of
symphonic music you can follow a
bassline or you can follow the strings
or you can follow the horns and they're
all harmoniously interrelated but
they're also separable okay so there is
an image that lurks in the Old Testament
and the image is the same image it's
roughly the same image as the image of
Marduk confronting Tiamat so for example
at the at the beginning God makes here's
here's how the beginning goes in the
beginning God created the heaven and the
earth and the earth was without form and
void and darkness was upon the face of
the deep and the Spirit of God moved
upon the face of the waters and God said
let there be light and there was light
okay so we got a look at the first few
lines here so this is God justifying
himself to job he says can you pull in
Leviathan with a fishhook or tie down
its tongue with a rope can you put a
cord through its nose or pierce its jaw
with a hook will it keep you begging for
mercy will it speak to you with gentle
words will it make an agreement with you
for you to take it as your slave for
life can you make a pet of it like a
bird or put it on a leash for the young
women in your house will traders barter
for it will they divide it up among the
merchants can you fill its hide with
harpoons or its head with fishing Spears
if you lay a hand on it you will
remember the struggle and never do it
again
any hope of subduing it is false the
mere sight of it is overpowering
no one is fierce enough to rouse it who
is then able to stand against me who has
a claim against me that I must pay
everything under heaven belongs to me
more computer trouble oh there we go I
will not fail to speak of leviathans
limbs its strength in its graceful form
who can strip off its outer coat who can
penetrate its double coat of armor who
dares open the doors of its mouth ringed
about with fearsome teeth its back has
rose
of shields tightly sealed together each
is so close to the next that no air can
pass between they are joined fast to one
another they cling together and cannot
be parted
it's snorting throws out flashes of
light its eyes are like the Rays of
Dawn's flame stream from its mouth
sparks of fire shoot out smoke pours
from its nostrils as from a boiling pot
over born burning reeds its breath sets
coals ablaze and flames dart from its
mouth strength resides in its neck
dismay goes before it the folds of its
flesh are tightly joined they are firm
and immovable its chest as as hard as
rock hard as a lower millstone when it
rises up the mighty are terrified they
retreat before it's thrashing the sword
that reaches it has no effect nor does
the spear or the dart or the javelin
iron it treats like straw and bronze
like a rotten wood arrows do not make it
flee sling stones are like chaff to it a
club seems to it but a piece of straw it
laughs at the rattling of the Lance its
undersides are jagged potsherds leaving
a trail in the mud like a threshing
sledge
it makes the depths churn like a boiling
cauldron and steez up the sea like a pot
of ointment it leaves a glistening wake
behind it one would think the deep had
white hair nothing on earth as its equal
a creature without fear it looks down on
all that are haughty and his king over
all that are proud well so what's God
doing he's describing what he defeated
in order to create the world
that's Marduk and Tiamat okay so that's
that's one reference like that all right
so now another reference like that this
is from Psalms 74 yet God is my king of
old working salvation in the midst of
the earth thou didst break the sea and
pieces by thy strength thou didst
shatter the heads of the sea monsters in
the waters thou did crush the heads of
Leviathan right that's the creature that
we just heard described thou gavest
him to be food to the folk inhabiting
the wilderness
now you remember so Tod when Marduk
defeats time at he cuts her into pieces
and makes the world out of her pieces
and here what's happening is that the
force that that encounters the Leviathan
is able to break it into pieces and feed
everyone with it now the reason I'm
telling you that in relationship to this
is because and the earth was what
without form and void and darkness was
upon the face of the deep
let me tell you a little bit about that
those lines before God's God begins to
create the world is Tohu Wabo who that's
from the Hebrew the word Tohu by itself
means emptiness or futility so there's a
psychological element to that a-and that
emptiness or futility in some sense is
what you confront when you're trying to
extract your life from the world it is
used to describe the desert wilderness
as well Touhou Wabo whoo chaos is the
condition that bara ordering remedies
okay so there's the idea in the first
verses that this initial chaos is being
ordered and the order is what makes the
world so the it's it's it's standard
cosmology order emerges out of chaos and
the thing that makes it emerges the Word
of God now
darkness and deep which is tale in
Hebrew are two of the three elements of
the chaos represented in Toa Touhou Wabo
who the third is the formless earth in
the ANU mulisch the deep is personified
as the goddess time out the enemy of
Marduk here it is the formless body of
primeval waters surrounding the
habitable world okay so but we know Thao
and Tiamat are the same word or at least
tale most derived from time out so the
idea that's presented at the beginning
of Genesis is the same it's an
abstracted and psychologize
representation of the story that the
Mesopotamians put forward so yahwah is
Marduk roughly speaking going out and
conquering the dragon of chaos and
making order out of it and then there
are these allusions later saying job and
in the Psalms of
doing exactly that conquering a
primordial monster and making the world
out of its pieces well so what does that
mean exactly well it means that the
highest ordering principle is the spirit
that goes out into the darkness or the
deep that encounters the dragon of chaos
because of obviously Leviathan is a
dragon and defeats it and feeds the
people as a consequence while we are
hunting creatures after all and in order
to establish our place in the world we
had to go out there and conquer the
Dragons of the wilderness you might
wonder why does it drag and breathe fire
well there's a bunch of reasons as far
as I can tell
fire is awe-inspiring so fire and a
terrible predator are the same thing
because they both inspire awe fire is
transforming
but credit like what's a good metaphor
for being bitten by a poisonous snake
well have you ever seen the wounds that
a poisonous snake produces if you're
bitten by them it's like someone took
your arm and incinerated it and so the
idea that a snake has fiery breath is
well let's call it close enough from a
metaphorical perspective right now God
is claiming to job that he's the spirit
that Clee that clears the wilderness and
then builds order out of chaos and
because because because he's the
embodiment of that spirit in some sense
job has no reason to ever question his
moral decisions it's something like that
in the story of job but the point that
that point will leave aside because it's
a more complicated issue the point is
that the writers of the Bible are trying
to dream up a representation of the
spirit of civilization that's the right
way to think about it you can think of
yahwah as the spirit of civilization and
what is that well it's the thing that
encounters the wilderness and makes
habitable order but then it's also the
spirit of the order itself and that's I
think why in Christianity there's a
representation of God the Father because
he's a representation of the the culture
that's generated after the the chaos is
ordered right you have the spirit that
goes out into chaos and orders and then
you have the spirit of the order and
then the spirit of the order and the
spirit of the ordering principle have to
figure out how to coexist that's partly
what the Egyptians were trying to figure
out
there's a dynamic relationship between
the culture and the spirit that
generates the culture and then you might
also ask should the culture be
superordinate or should the spirit that
generates the culture be superordinate
and the answer seems to be the emergent
answer seems to be that the spirit that
generates the culture should be
superordinate to the spirit of the
culture it's something like that and
that's also why I think that one of the
brilliant discoveries let's say of
Western individualistic civilization is
that the group is there to serve the
individual because the individual is the
thing that revivify is the group so with
each depend on the other integrally but
if you subordinate the individual to the
group then the group stagnates and dies
and so that's a very bad long-term
strategy even though the group and
belonging to the group is clearly
necessary you need to uphold the values
of the group but the values of the group
should be subordinated to producing the
individual who gives the group vision
and the Mesopotamians figure that out
the Egyptians figured that out we've
figured it out we just don't know that
we figured it out and it's not a mere
arbitrary supposition all right so I
should show you because this is actually
interesting I think perhaps good I want
to show you what the cosmology what
people considered to cause the the the
the the structure of the initial order
because it's kind of interesting and God
said let there be a firmament in the
midst of the waters and let it divide
the waters from the waters
and God made the firmament and divided
the waters which were under the
firmament from the waters which were
above the firmament and it was so and
God called the firmament heaven and the
evening in the morning were the second
day
well so what are they thinking about
well that's the sort of classical view
of the world it's something like that is
that there's a disc that's the disc we
inhabit and there's land that's the disc
and under the disc there's water fresh
water and then under that there's the
ocean and then on top of that there's a
dome and that's the sky
that's the firmament that's heaven and
there's water above that
well obviously because it rains so there
has to be water up there so that's the
way the cosmos was conceptualized just
so you know now it's a phenomenological
conceptualization because that's what it
looks like right and you might say well
that's wrong it's like well yes it's
it's wrong in a functional sort of way
it's right from a phenomenological
perspective but it's wrong from a all
from a scientific perspective was never
designed to be a scientific perspective
so all right so we won't bother with
this part will we'll start here so God
makes animals and plants and all of that
and then at the end of it this is on
which day sixth day God said let us make
man in our image after our likeness and
let them have dominion over the fish of
the sea and the fowl of the air and over
the cattle and all of the earth and over
every creeping thing that creepeth upon
the earth
okay well the relevant there's two
relevant issues there one is let us make
man in our image after our likeness well
what exactly does that mean well we've
already we've already encountered that
to some degree we've already encountered
what the nature of the Spirit of God is
in this story the nature of the Spirit
of God that creates order out of chaos
is the thing that creates order out of
chaos and so that the statement here is
that there's something about human
beings that partakes in that now when I
started unpacking this I thought okay
look there's an idea
that's at the root of our legal system
and so our legal system is the
articulation of the patterns by which we
live and to a fair degree it's it's an
evolved system it's a culturally
constructed system but it's an evolved
system as well and it's predicated on
the idea that there's something about
the individual that the law has to
respect well so the question is well is
that just an arbitrary supposition
because that's really the question it's
the same question as is Western
civilization founded on something that's
a rock or is it just founded on
something that's an opinion well it's
the same question with regards to the
law the law assumes that there's
something about you that's sovereign
even if
you're a murderer you have inalienable
rights now you think that is a bloody
weird thing for any sort of system to
have come up with because the idea that
if you're the ultimate in malevolent
transgressors that you still have some
sort of sovereign value it's like that
is such an unlikely thing for people to
think up that you really have to think a
long time about how that might have come
to be well there's an idea here that's
the idea is that there's something about
human beings men and women you know
because people often complain about the
patriarchal structure of the Bible it's
based on a misapprehension of
anthropology that was popularized by
someone named gimme you toss at UCLA it
says we're forever and for her
perspective there's not a shred of
historical evidence although there's
some psychological truth in it in in
Genesis both men and women are created
in the image of God that's quite a
remarkable thing I think it's a rich a
remarkable part of the document because
it's not what you'd expect from a
patriarchal you know from a from a
document that was designed to do nothing
but extend the Dominion of the
patriarchy it's like you will left women
with the damned cattle that would have
made things a lot easier and that isn't
what happened so both men and women have
this image and what's the image well
that's the image of the thing that can
order chaos and so it's necessary to
treat you as if you have intrinsic value
because the fact that you can partake in
the process of mediating between order
and chaos means that you're basically
the salvation of society that's what it
means and so society can't impose on you
to to greater degree because you are too
valuable for even the law to push
arbitrarily past a certain point now
then you have to think this and this is
this is this is where you really have to
think about what you believe do you
believe that or not because there's not
much difference really technically
speaking there's not much difference
than that between that and believing
these stories it depends bloody well
what you mean by believe they're not
scientific representations of an
evolutionary process obviously the
people who came up with them words
scientists so whatever they are they're
not that but they're making a
proposition that's not an accidental
proposition and we
that partly because it's rooted so
deeply in these ancient stories we have
no idea how old the Mesopotamian story
is you know it's the oldest story we
have in written form so we know that but
god only knows how old it is it's part
of an oral tradition and these oral
traditions can be look the same
Carver gave me a big thing called a sea
suit and it's a man in the middle of a
double headed sea serpent right so there
there that's 14,000 years old that came
from Siberia it's the same bloody idea
it's the same idea
so these ideas aren't arbitrary so the
question is well are they true well then
the question is what the hell do you
mean by true because it comes down to
that is it true that habitable order is
dependent on the spirit that moves into
the unknown and takes the Leviathan and
chops it into pieces and distributes it
and the answer to that is yes that's
true as far as I can tell and do you
mean is it literally true well it's just
true as things get that's how we got
here we got here because people went
into the unknown they conquered what was
out there they took what was of utility
from that they brought it back and they
shared it with the community that's why
we're here that is the central story of
humankind and that's still what we do
you know we're not exactly necessarily
going out to conquer an embodied monster
although we do that if we hunt for
example but you know most of us don't do
that anymore but to the degree that
you're an explorer in the in the
intellectual realm you're still going
out into the unknown and conquering
what's out there looming like maybe it's
it's the cure for a disease you're
looking that right in the face you're
trying to decompose it and break it into
its parts you're trying to understand
and then you're trying to tell everybody
what you found well and everybody Pat's
you on the back and says well you're
you're you're a brave Explorer of the
unknown well that is exactly the sort of
thing that we should be fostering and
it's the thing that we all admire so
okay so that happens on the sixth day
and so now we know human beings are made
in God's image well what does that mean
exactly
I think I think what it means a
reasonable way of thinking about it you
can think about it like the genie the
genie has this tremendous amount of
power that's constrained in a very small
space and genie and genius are the same
word roughly speaking so the genius is
that your genius is the genie that
inhabits you right it's this logo spirit
it's an it's put in a very small
container you see that idea represented
in the Christian conception of the
relationship between Christ and God
because there's an idea that God had to
empty himself out in order to fit into
the body of Christ it's something like
that they call that kenosis that's a
technical word and what it seems to be
the idea that you're a looks like you're
a low-resolution representation of the
ultimate spirit that that encounters the
unknown it's something like that it's a
very smart idea and you could say maybe
that's what human beings have in common
is that that that we reach an embodiment
of that spirit for lack of a better word
so okay so then God makes the God makes
human beings male and female makes them
in his own image and is happy about them
and says well you're gonna dominate the
world which you know people like David
Suzuki read that to say you should go
out and dominate the world because they
read that kind of patriarchal oppression
into the text but this is more a
description of how things are going to
be then whether or not they should be
that way so anyways that's the sixth day
the seventh day God rests right so
that's the origin of the week roughly
speaking so okay that's one story
there's two creation stories in Genesis
and they actually don't match completely
in their structure and what happened was
someone they call the redactor maybe it
was a bunch of people we don't know
took creation story one and creation
story two from different places and
thought well these are sort of the same
and they're sort of different and people
are going to be unhappy if we dispense
with this one and they're going to be
unhappy if we dispense this this one but
they don't make sense together so let's
see if we can put them in some kind of
order that makes a proximate sense and
they took the newer one and put it
second and took the sorry they took the
older one
at second and put took the newer one and
put it first so Adam and Eve is an older
story than the story that I just told
you so but it's a different story it's
written in a different style but it's
been more or less brought into narrative
coherence with the first story so and
you could say at the level of the
sentence there is paradoxes but at the
level of the chapter let's say the
stories make sense
so okay so what happens up there went
from the earth amidst and it watered the
whole face of the ground and the Lord
God formed man of the dust of the ground
and breathed into his nostrils the
breath of life and man became a living
soul there's an identity in this archaic
sort of thought between breath and
spirit right respiration spirit
inspiration spirit NUMA like pneumatic
tire spirit the breath contains the
spirit well why is that well because
when people died the breath leaves their
body and so it's an easy thing to
identify that with the animating spirit
right now anima means spirit as well so
so that's the phenomenological reality
of the story and Lord God planted a
garden eastward in Eden and there he put
the man whom he had formed Eden means
well watered place well why well where
do you want to live these are desert
people right who are writing this well
what do they want they want an oasis
what's a know what's an oasis it's a
garden with water well you're gonna
gonna live somewhere it's not gonna be
out in the middle of the damn desert you
want to be in a garden that's watered
and then you could say you also be in a
walled garden that's protected and
that's what paradise means Paradiso
means walled garden so this initial
paradise is a walled garden why walled
order it's culture nature what does it
mean well that's the natural environment
of human beings it's a it's the optimal
balance between culture and nature
that's what a walled garden is with
enough water flowing in it to keep it to
keep it fertile and that water is also
chaos right there has to be it can't be
static and dry and solid and stale there
has to be some living element to it so
so it's a walled place that the water
can still fructify and out of the ground
made the Lord God to grow
every tree that is pleasant to the sight
so it's also full of trees this is our
natural habitat and good for food The
Tree of Life also in the midst of the
garden and the tree of the knowledge of
good and evil so these are two trees
they bring forth fruit that produce
something one produces the knowledge of
good and evil and the other produces
eternal life
so why well I'll get to that Amit and a
river went out of Eden to water the
garden and from thence it was parted and
became into four heads we won't bother
with that
so now God is having a little chat
without him and he says look you can eat
every tree of the garden except one of
the tree of the knowledge of good and
evil you you don't eat that because in
the day you eat you'll surely die
so you might ask well why is the tree
put there to begin with and well the
answer to that is who the hell knows
that's how the story portrays it we
don't know and the Lord God said it is
not good that the man should be alone I
will make help meet for him and out of
the ground the Lord God formed every
beast of the field in every fall of the
air and brought them unto Adam to see
what he would call them and whatsoever
Adam called every living creature that
was the name thereof so that's an echo
of the idea of the power of the word
right so even though these stories are
from different traditions their separate
traditions you see at the beginning that
God uses his word to bring order out of
chaos and then he allows Adam in some
sense to do the same thing is that
there's this unarticulated plethora of
being and the man comes along and says
that's that that's that that's that and
that brings them into a higher order
form of being so it's a it's a
replication of the creation in a in a
shrunken form and Adam gave names to all
the cattle cattle are just anything that
has four legs roughly speaking and to
the fowl of the air and to every beast
of the field but for Adam there was not
found to help meet for him and the goat
Lord God caused a deep sleep to fall
upon Adam and he slept and he took one
of his ribs and closed up the flesh
instead thereof and the rib which the
Lord God had taken from man made he a
woman and brought her unto the man and
Adam said this is now bone of my bones
and flesh of my flesh she shall be
called woman because she was taken out
of man and then there's an injunction
therefore a man shall leave his father
and his mother and shall cleave unto his
wife and they shall be one flesh while
there's also a there's a moral
injunction there and so the idea is that
the two beings that have been created or
actually not whole until they're one
thing right and once they're joined
together that's supposed to be one thing
and that one thing is actually a more
perfect entity than the two things that
are apart so and that's actually part of
the sacred basis of the idea of
monogamous relationships in Western
culture and they were both naked the man
and his wife and we're not ashamed a
crucial piece of information so what
exactly does that mean
well the first question is what does it
mean to be naked and so that's something
that I thought about a lot in relation
and there's a relationship there with
shame so the first question is what does
it mean to be naked and the second
question is what does it mean to be not
ashamed of that well there's an there is
a I would say there's an implication of
a kind of unconsciousness so Adam and
Eve exists in this paradisal state but
they they don't they don't they don't
have the capacity for self-reflection
there's no self-consciousness here well
why would I say that because there's
very little difference between
self-consciousness and shame in fact if
you do psychometric analysis of the
state of self-consciousness it loads
with neuroticism so loads with anxiety
and emotional pain so to become
self-conscious what does it mean to
become self-conscious it me becomes it
means you become aware one way of
thinking about it is you become aware of
your vulnerability or another is that
you become aware of your insufficiency
okay so let's say that you're standing
up in front of a crowd talking and you
become self-conscious what happens well
first of all you can't talk anymore
the second is he kind of fall inside and
the third is you feel ashamed and the
fourth is that you retreat and you look
down so it's a low status operation and
it's associated with heightened anxiety
and so then you might say well why would
you become self-conscious before a crowd
well the answer is they can see you
right and they can judge you and you can
make an error in front of them and you
can make a fool of yourself so they put
you down that you can you can display
yourself in a manner that ratchets you
down the dominance hierarchy that's to
become self-conscious and so well at
least you have the advantage of being
covered up in front of the crowd but
let's say all of a sudden you're
stripped of your clothes
so what's the problem with that well all
of your insufficiencies let's say are on
painful display you can be evaluated by
everyone but even more importantly than
that if possible is that clothes
actually protect the most vulnerable
parts of you human beings are upright
animals right
we're very strange animals you take a
cat or a dog
they're basically armored the part of
them that you see their back is heavily
armored heavily protected human being
stretched up right and so the softest
part of parts of us are there for
display but also we're displayed as
sexual creatures too and so to become to
be naked and not ashamed of it is to
lack self-consciousness so the idea is
that the Adam and Eve in the original
state in the garden lacked
self-consciousness now the serpent was
more subtle subtle is an interesting
word here because it means kind of fog
like and and vague and difficult to
detect so it's something that that lurks
and is hidden so that's what the serpent
is it sits in the domain of hidden
things than any beast of the field which
the Lord God had made and the serpent
said unto the woman hey hasn't God said
you shouldn't eat of every tree of the
garden and the woman said we may eat of
the fruit of the trees of the garden but
of the fruit of the tree which is in the
middle of the garden the central fruit
God has said you shall not eat of it
neither shall you touch it lest you die
and the serpent said unto the woman you
shall not surely die for God knows that
in the day you eat thereof then your
eyes will be opened and you will be as
God's knowing good and evil all right so
there's another implication there we
already saw that there's an implication
that Adam and Eve are not self conscious
and now there's the implication that
their eyes aren't open or at least that
they're not open fully in some sense
they're not open for example to the
knowledge of good and
evil and that seems to be associated
somehow with death in some strange way
okay so and it's the serpent talking to
the woman so the serpent taught is that
is the tempter of the woman so the
question is why in the world would that
be I showed you those representations of
Mary right holding the infant up in the
air with her foot on the snake so you
think well who's more self-conscious
women are men and the answer to that is
women are more self-conscious than men
and even further you might say that
women taught men to be self-conscious
and I believe that to be the case
maybe babies taught women to be
self-conscious but women taught men to
be self-conscious and they still teach
them that all the time because there's
nothing that makes a man more
self-conscious that to be rejected by a
woman that he desires so the woman is
always offering self-consciousness to
men and it isn't necessarily a gift that
they exactly appreciate and that motif
of course runs through the Adam and Eve
story centrally because Eve is damned
forever in some sense for making out
himself conscious well he didn't want to
be self-conscious things were pretty
good when his eyes were closed and he
was wandering around not worrying about
whether he was naked or not well the
women became self-conscious why because
of snakes
well maybe right maybe that's exactly
what happened you know she imagined
we're being preyed upon for millions of
years by predatory reptiles right and we
become more and more alert to threat and
more and more alert to threat and then
one day we get so alert to threat that
we can see threat lurking in the future
and then all of a sudden we become aware
of the future and then we become aware
of death and then we're really
self-conscious but it's pretty good if
you want to keep the snakes down which
we've been doing quite successfully ever
since then but it's a big price to pay
we got so damn sensitive to threat that
we were finally able to conceive the
ultimate threat not proximal threats but
the fact of threat itself and the fact
of mortality itself and the fact of
finitude itself and maybe women learned
that because they become painfully aware
of the mortal limitations of their
infants first right this small thing
could die could end a little and
certainly as an object of predation and
you can imagine God
knows how many infants human-beings lost
to predators I mean I told you at one
point I believe that there was a cat
that was found that had a that had a
that had a skull and jaws that were
specialized for biting the skulls of
protohumans one long tooth at the back
that would drive right through the back
of the skull so the cat could put its
teeth here and drive the tooth right
into the back of the skull so you know
that's a good enough dragon for our for
all for our intents and purposes I would
say anyways the snake comes along and
opens the woman's eyes when the woman
saw that the tree was good for food and
that was pleasant to the eye and a
treated to be desired to make one wise
she took of the fruit thereof and did
eat and gave also unto her husband with
her and he did eat and the eyes of both
of them were opened and they knew that
they were naked and they sewed fig
leaves together and made themselves
aprons well there's a lot happening in
those few lines now there's a fruit
thing going on there
snake and fruit okay so we know from
Lynn is Bell hypothetically that the
reason that primates like us developed
our intense vision is because we
co-evolved with snakes so the snakes
opened their eyes what about fruit color
vision right why to detect ripe fruit we
know that and our women and ripe fruit
the same well they're the same insofar
as it was women offering the ripe fruit
and that's undoubtedly something that
happened you know that the hypothetical
idea is the male's hunt and bring home
protein the women gather what are they
gathering well they're gathering at
minimum ripe fruit and then what are
they doing they're sharing it well you
also bring about a moral obligation when
you're sharing food right there's an
invitation to reciprocity there and so
the fact that women were sharing let's
say ripe fruit with men also brings them
into their what would you call builds up
the basis for the potential of a
reciprocal moral obligation it's
something like that and the problem
again for men with being allied with
women and infants is that it also
heightens their self-consciousness
because you're a lot tougher and more
indomitable say if there's just you but
as soon as you have
wife say and then you also have an
infant well all the burden of their
self-consciousness and their
vulnerability is placed upon you well
it's a hell of a bargain well why did
men accept the bargain well it's partly
because women stood in front of them
offering them fruit right well part of
the price that the men paid for that was
to wake the hell up well who the hell
wants that it's a lot more it's a lot
more calming to remain asleep with no
knowledge of the sort of burden of
mortality that you would bear if you
became self-conscious so fine so now
they're done with it they the snake and
the fruit woke them up and they can see
and the scales drop from the rise and so
we can really see well so what does that
mean how our brain is visual is devoted
to visual processing so as well as long
as as our eyes got better our brain got
bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger
what happens when it gets big enough
well not only can you see you can Metis
see it's you can start to see into the
future well that's exactly what happened
to us
not only could we see with our eyes we
could see with our imagination and our
imagination is or you can see with your
eyes closed right close your eyes bring
up a vision you can imagine the future
well what do you see you're seeing a
potential future with your eyes closed
the circuitry is there once it's
developed you can use it to imagine you
can project your project your vision
into places that don't even exist and
you can start to conceptualize the
future what happens when you
conceptualize the future well this is a
I'm spoiling the punchline you have to
work because you can see the future
coming you think all the future is
coming it isn't just the present anymore
I don't have to just worry about whether
or not I'm hungry right now I'm gonna
have to worry about whether I'm hungry
tomorrow and next week and next month
and next year and for me and for my wife
and for my child and for the community
it's like you can forget about your
day-to-day existence in paradise at that
point there's no evidence that people in
industrialized societies are happier
than people in non industrialized
societies in fact quite the contrary
we're less happy why well because we
fully and constantly bear the burden of
the future
well that's good because we don't die
and we live maybe 30 years longer and we
have fewer horrible diseases and all of
that but that doesn't mean it's any
picnic you have to carry that along with
you wherever you go that's the burden of
self-consciousness right and that's
exactly what happens when God finds out
that Adam and Eve have become
self-conscious before one of the first
things he says is haha jigs up now man
you're gonna be working forever toiling
forever
it's your destiny there's no escaping
from it well human beings work what does
that mean they sacrifice the present for
the future and that's partly as soon as
this happens like the next story which
is Cain and Abel you see the motif of
sacrifice emerge write that story
circulates around the motif of sacrifice
sacrifice the present for the future
well what's the price you pay you don't
get the present that's a big price right
because what you do is what you're doing
essentially is you're taking all the
potential suffering of the future and
putting it into the present all the time
well so what happens well maybe you live
longer and you live healthier but you're
not without the burden that that puts on
you so the eyes of them were both opened
and they knew they were naked well so
what does that mean well what does naked
mean it means you know you're vulnerable
that's exactly what it means they know
they're vulnerable so they so fig leaves
together and make themselves aprons so
what happens is they wake up their eyes
open they know they're vulnerable so
they discover the future they discover
their vulnerability extended into the
future and the first thing they do is
build culture right that's the fig
leaves it's like okay here's the
vulnerability we put a barrier between
us in the world it's like a wall right
because this is externalized clothing
that's one way of thinking about it and
so to put that clothing on this is
clothing as a human Universal by the way
now sometimes it's only used for
decorative purposes but far more often
especially in cold climates it's used
for protection so to clothe yourself is
to recognize your vulnerability and to
use culture to hold it at bay so find
they make themselves aprons and they
heard the voice of the Lord God walking
in the garden in the cool of the day and
Adam and his wife hid themselves
from the presence of the Lord God among
the trees of the garden okay so before
Adam and Eve wake up before they realize
they're vulnerable they don't hide from
God so what does that mean well he's the
spirit that goes into the unknown - to -
to conquer it and to make the world okay
so let's say that's what you're supposed
to do you're supposed to mediate between
chaos and order
okay and you're supposed to do that
forthrightly so then the question is
what the hell is stopping you and that
answer is easy your knowledge of your
vulnerability
obviously that's what's stopping you
it's like why aren't you courageous and
forthright well because you can be cut
off at the knees and terribly hurt and
so you're gonna shrink back from that
responsibility and it's no bloody wonder
right it's it's it's obviously what's
going to happen so Lord God calls them
to Adam so he's trying to what that
means - for the for God to call on you
is to say for God to say I want to act
through you or I want to act with you
well that spirit let's say well Adam
says I heard I heard God says to Adam
where are you and Adam says I heard your
voice in the garden right I heard the
call but I was afraid because I was
naked and I hid myself it's like yes
that's exactly what human beings are
like that's precisely exactly what we're
like we hear the call but we hide and we
have the thing is it's there's good
reason for it it's not something trivial
and God said who told you you were naked
did you eat the tree that I told you
shouldn't eat and the man says the man
doesn't come off very well in this
particular phrase as far as I'm
concerned and there's actually quite
this is actually quite a comedic story
except that it's also a catastrophic
tragedy it's like God calls out him out
like what's with you now you know you're
hiding from me why and the first thing
out him does it says it's her fault it's
her fault she made me self-conscious
well I see that in resentful men all the
time they're very antipathy towards
women and they blame their misery and
resentment on the fact that women won't
have anything to do with them while the
women
making them self-conscious for not being
all they should be because the women
think why should I bother with you if
you're not the embodiment of the spirit
that will move into the unknown and and
face the Leviathan which is exactly what
she should be saying and you're thinking
well I don't want to have anything to do
with that but I'd like women to like me
anyways it's like well good luck with
that so that doesn't work out and so
instead of getting your act together you
say those goddamn women that's exactly
what Adam says to God he said but don't
don't be laying this on my feet it's the
woman you made her she made me all
self-conscious and cowardly
it's like brilliant great wonderful and
God says to the woman what did you do
and the woman said well it was it was
the serpent that that confused me and
and I ate well it's like actually I'm a
little more sympathetic to her than to
Adam all things considered because after
all she was trying to deal with the damn
snake right and we find out that the
snake is not only the thing that preys
upon her infants but as the tradition
developed it's identified with Satan
himself so and that's the snake in every
soul that's the right way of thinking
about that so she had her reasons
but doesn't matter you pay whether you
have your reasons or not and so God says
to the serpent because you've done this
you're cursed above all cattle and above
every beast of the field upon the belly
shalt thou go and dust shalt thou eat
all the days of thy life so first of all
the serpent seems to have legs right and
then it's turned into a snake and that's
actually how it worked by the way
because snakes had legs and they lost
them now you know I'm not trying to say
that this story necessarily represents
that but it's an interesting parallel
and he tells the snake I'll put enmity
between thee and the woman and between
thy seed and her seed it shall bruise
thy head and thou shalt bruise his heel
well yes well that's the snake striking
right and the fact that when human being
see snakes they want to just like The
Simpsons
whacking day right it's time to get rid
of the snakes and that's why the many
great Saints are those who drive the
snakes from the land like st. Patrick or
Saint George and the dragon and it's the
same representation of the hero moving
out into the wilderness and confronting
the predatory the predatory predatory
potential is the right way of thinking
about it all right unto the woman he
said
I will greatly multiply thy sorrow and
thy conception in sorrow thou shalt
bring forth children and thy desire to
be shall be to thy husband and he shall
rule over thee well that's a statement
of Destiny not a statement of the way it
should be so what does it mean I will
greatly multiply thy sorrow and thy
conception
well self-consciousness will do that
because of course women are fully aware
of exactly how fragile their infants are
so that's a big problem in sorrow thou
shalt bring forth children
that's something particular to human
women right and here's why the price we
paid for the rapid expansion of our
brain which is also something that gave
us this self-consciousness and vision
meant that there's an evolutionary arms
race between the pelvic width of women
and the hole in the center of the pelvis
and the infant's head so what happens is
the infant is born far too young for a
mammal of our size because if it was
Benny older the head would be too big
the pelvis would have to be too wide
it's structural stability would be
compromised and then women couldn't run
so right now women are at the maximum
for hip-width in terms of their ability
to run so what's happened is that
infants have had to be born younger with
a compressible head so you know the
bones of an infant's collar joined
together and sometimes after babies are
born their head is actually almost
cone-shaped because of the tremendous
pressure that was exerted on their head
during the during the birthing process
and of course that's killed innumerable
women right I mean women's life
expectancy before what the latter half
of the 20th century was way below men
because they died in childbirth all the
time and why well it's a it's a very
what do you call that it's a it's it's a
very narrow gateway and the price that
women pay for it is very high risk of
death very high risk of sorrow because
of death of children in in childbirth
and also extraordinarily extraordinary
pain in giving birth so that's the price
women pay for having vision and being
self-conscious well that's and then
worse they desire their husband and
he'll rule over them well whether or not
that's
good or bad it doesn't matter guards
statement is that's how it's going to be
well partly that's because as far as I
can tell there isn't really women
roughly speaking there's women with
infants and a woman with an infant is
compromised in terms of her what
independent individuality to a
remarkable degree because the infant is
dependent absolutely dependent
absolutely dependent for a year and then
unbelievably dependent for like eight
years after that and then still pretty
dependent for another five so once you
have an infant it's no longer you and
I've talked to lots of women for whom
that was a great relief by the way
because it actually is somewhat of a
relief to now not be the center of
everything you know if you go visit your
in-laws for example and you have a baby
it's like they pay attention to the baby
your parents will do the same thing it's
kind of nice to have that happen but
it's still an absolute catastrophe for
you as an independent being and you're
not going to go out in the forest and
hunt down dragons when you have an
infant so even if you could do it you're
not gonna do it and so that's basically
what that's statement outlines and then
to atomy says because you listen to your
wife an eighth of that tree which I said
you know maybe that's not such a good
idea
curse it is the ground for thy sake in
sorrow shalt thou eat of it all the days
of they light of thy life thorns also
and thistles shall it bring forth to
thee and thou shalt eat the herb of the
field in the sweat of thy face shalt
thou eat bread till thou return into the
ground that's the death part for out of
it was thou taken for dust thou art and
unto dust thou shalt thou return and I
missed one thing about that when the
serpent this took me a long time to
figure out I think I've mentioned it
already but it's worth reviewing the
serpent tells Eve that if she eats from
the fruit of the tree then her eyes will
be open and she'll be as God's knowing
good and evil
well the serpent doesn't say well you'll
be as as gods insofar as knowing good
and evil but you'll die so you only get
half the gift and so then I thought well
there's this weird Minter mingling of of
occurrences in the story there's the
development of vision
the development of self-consciousness
there's the knowledge of nakedness
there's the emergence of work there's
the emergence of pain and suffering in
childbirth and there's knowledge of good
and evil I thought for ages I thought
what the hell what the hell what's going
on there why is there an emphasis on
moral knowledge what does this have to
do with moral knowledge and the
implication is that in the initial state
of unconsciousness there was no moral
knowledge and I think of that as an
animal-like State right there's no moral
knowledge in animals
you don't think well that evil cat you
don't ever think that even if it's
acting like a predator even if it's
playing with its prey you don't
attribute moral knowledge to the cat
because you say well it doesn't know
what it's doing it doesn't understand
what it's doing which is to say it acts
it out but it can't represent it or
maybe even more it acts it out but it
can't represent it and it certainly
can't analyze its representation it
doesn't have that level of capacity but
we do so there's that's associated with
moral knowledge to some degree why
knowledge of good and evil I thought all
right here's what it is let's think
about what you would consider
reprehensible universally you could say
how is this torturing an infant I would
consider that virtually universally
reprehensible wouldn't you say
okay so we'll accept that as a
reasonable definition so then the
question is one why would you do it
we'll leave that aside for a moment to
how do you know how to do it that's the
issue and that's easy once I know how I
can be hurt because I'm aware of my own
vulnerability I know how you can be hurt
and I can make it into a game and I can
prolong it forever and I can do it the
worst possible way and that's why when
you open your eyes and you know your
vulnerability and your nakedness that
you immediately have the knowledge of
good and evil and so then evil becomes
something like well there's tragedy in
life fine earthquakes cancer disease all
those terrible things that's different
than me deciding that I'm going to make
you miserable
the one is while you're a limited
creature in an unlimited world you're
going to get hurt because of that and
maybe there's ways that you can be that
will enable you to transcend that at
least to some degree and still have the
benefit
of being that's entirely different than
me deciding that things are going to go
a lot worse for you than they might and
human beings are capable I don't know if
you've ever gone to some of the dungeon
torture dungeons in Europe boy those are
fun places to go you think you take the
most malevolent person you possibly
could and then have a little convention
of those people and then get them to
think up the worst possible things that
they could possibly devise and then you
have the instruments of torture that in
a in a medieval torture dungeon right
it's an art form and you think well why
do people why are people willing to
inflict that on one another well and
we'll talk about that next time when we
talk about the story of Cain and Abel
because I think it holds the secret to
that and in the meantime I'll stop with
this story but I want to tell you the
story of the Buddha because it maps on
to it very nicely so what do you have
you have you have a protected space
there's unconscious beings in a
protected space something comes in in
the form of the serpent to reveal death
to view to reveal vulnerability and
death right and then the paradise comes
to an end the human beings are
eliminated from it and they don't get to
come back so God puts angels with
flaming swords at the at the at the
gateway to paradise so that people
cannot come back yet it isn't obvious
what that means except that there's got
to be some sort of trial by fire before
re-entering paradise but we can leave
that alone for a moment so that's the
basic structure of this story
unconscious human beings emergence of
knowledge realization of death and
suffering and the elimination of the
paradise right okay so now I'll read you
the story of the Buddha the father of
Prince Gautama the Buddha Savior of the
Orient determined to protect his son
from desperate knowledge and tragic
awareness built for him and enclosed
pavilion a walled garden of earthly
delights okay so the story goes that an
angel visited Buddha's father and said
that he's going to have a son and the
son is either going to become the
greatest ruler that the world has ever
seen or a spiritual leader and the
father being a practical man thought
where there's no bloody way I want my
son to be some like wandering spiritual
leader I want him to be the greatest
king that the world has ever seen
okay and so
the father decides how am I going to get
my son to be the greatest ruler the
world has ever seen
I better get him to fall in love with
the world because then he's not gonna go
traipsing after some sort of half-witted
spiritual knowledge he's gonna stick to
practical tasks right that's something
that a father should do to some degrees
orient you in the world right and maybe
shouldn't subvert your your spiritual
development to any great degree but
there's a practical element to this and
and so anyways that's how it works and
so that's what happens the the the
father builds this city of perfection
and he eliminates from it everything
that's a reminder of the suffering
that's associated with life so the only
thing that's allowed the only creatures
that are allowed to be in there the only
people that are allowed to be in there
are healthy young and happy people so
the buddha grows up surrounded by
nothing but the positive elements of
life well you think well what does that
mean well it's akin to the paradise idea
obviously walled enclosure of paradise
where there's no death but there's more
to it than that - it's also in some
sense what a good father would do what
do you do with your young children
well you don't expose them to death and
decay at every step of the way right do
you you build a protected world for them
like a walled enclosure and you only
keep what's healthy and life-giving
inside of it and you don't expose them
to things that they can't tolerate you
know maybe you don't take a
three-year-old to a funeral now maybe
you do but maybe you don't there's
things that you don't expect them to be
able to cope with you regulate what
they're allowed to watch you're not
going to show them the TEC Texas
Chainsaw Massacre when they're four
years old right so so you're staving off
knowledge of mortality and death and so
he's just being a good father in many
ways here all signs of decay and
degeneration were thus kept hidden from
the prints emerged in the immediate
pleasures of the senses in physical love
and dance and music and beauty and
pleasure
Gautama grew to maturity protected
absolutely from the limitations of
mortal being
however he grew curious despite his
father's most particularly and will and
resolved to leave his seductive prison
well it's that curiosity element it's
the same thing that lurks in the Adam
and Eve story it's like God tells
I'm Eve see that tree over there don't
be bothering with it well you know
what's gonna happen with human beings
especially if there's a snake associated
with it they're gonna be over there
right away
check in that place out and that's
exactly what happens with the Buddhists
like he's raised to be healthy and what
is what's the consequence of that is
that the fact that he's healthy makes
him look for what's beyond the protected
confines of the thing that made him
healthy it's like what's like even in
the Geppetto story you know where
Geppetto paints on Pinocchio's mouth and
he's ready to go he puts him outside the
next day and Pinocchio is ready to run
away with all the kids right so the
consequence of raising a child in a
healthy way is that the child is going
to be curious enough to go out there and
look for some trouble and we actually
know that because there is follow-up
studies of teenagers you imagine that
there's teenagers who never break any
rules and then there's teenagers who
break all the rules okay
these teenagers don't do very well
introverted depressed anxious depressed
sorry I said that twice these ones are
antisocial the ones in the middle that's
what you want you want your damn
teenager to get out of the paradisal
confines of your house and they go
causes some trouble and to investigate
maybe you don't want to know about it
any more than you have to you don't want
them to be breaking rules all the time
and you don't want them to be so timid
and oppressed that they can't make a
move on their own and never make a
mistake so the the paradoxical thing
here and it's sort of echoed out this is
why I like these two stories
back-to-back is like if you give people
what they want then the first thing
they're gonna do is try to get beyond it
and Dostoevsky says the same thing in
notes from underground he says if you
gave people everything they wanted
pure utopia so he says so that they're
there sitting in a pool of bliss with
nothing but bubbles of happiness coming
up from the surface and all they have to
do is eat cake and busy themselves with
the continuation of the species dosti
said Dostoyevsky's observation is the
first thing that people would do is find
something to smash that with just so
that something interesting and perverse
could happen it's like well yes where
were creatures that are designed to
encounter the unknown we want to keep
moving beyond what we have even if we
have what we have is
what we want and maybe that's part
because we're oriented towards the
future we think well this is great but
it's not good enough it's great but it's
not good enough there's always something
more that drives us forward well so
that's what happens with the Buddha he
gets curious he sees the walls he thinks
there's walls there's probably something
outside of those walls so then he goes
to his father and he says I'm I want to
go outside what's outside and his father
says no how you don't want to go outside
and Buddha says yeah well I really do
want to go outside and his father knows
that unless he lets him go outside he's
going to climb over the walls and so the
father decides he's gonna let him go
outside because he can fix everything
out there first so he goes outside it's
like the Chinese preparing for the
Olympics you know when they sprayed the
grass with with with green paint got rid
of all the homeless people it's the same
thing so he goes outside the city and he
tells everyone all right
old people sick people dying people hit
the road we don't want to see you for a
while clean all this out we want the
attractive people around the sides of
the roads like waving palm fronds and
all of that and so when my son comes out
he's going to see nothing but what's
good and so he gets that all arranged
and lets his son go outside now his son
goes outside in this little chariot
thing and he has a someone with him now
unbeknownst to his father that person
that's with him is an emissary of the
gods and so in a perverse way he plays
the same role as the serpent in the
story of Adam and Eve and the gods have
already arranged so that the father's
carer is going to be insufficient and
it's the snake in the garden idea it's
like no matter how much care you take to
make things perfect some of the some of
what what you're excluding is going to
come back in so anyways
Buddha goes outside and and he's in his
chariot and preparations were made to
gild his chosen road to cover the
adventurous path with flowers and to
display for his admiration and
preoccupation the fairest women of the
kingdom the prince set out with full
retinue in the shielded comfort of a
chaperone chariot and delighted in the
panorama previously prepared for him the
gods however decided to disrupt these
most carefully laid plans and sent an
aged man
hobble in full view alongside the road
the princes fascinated gaze fell upon
the ancient interloper
compelled by curiosity asked his
attendant what is that creature
stumbling shabby Benton broken beside my
retinue and the attendant answered that
is a man like other men who was born an
infant became a child a youth a husband
a father a father of fathers he has
become old subject to destruction of his
beauty his will and the possibilities of
life like other men you say hesitantly
inquired the prince that means this will
happen to me and the attendant answered
inevitably with the passage of time well
that's the end of that party the world
collapses in on Buda and paying he
hightails at home well what does that
mean well that's what children do
roughly speaking is there around there
mother there they've got security there
they go out into the unknown they
encounter something that's just a little
bit too much for them bang they come
home they get all padded back into shape
and hugged and taken care of
hugging children and patting them is
actually analgesic it actually reduces
pain unsurprisingly that's what you do
with someone who's grieving right so you
hug them because grief is pain so so
they you know you pat them they get rid
of their pain they get rid of their
anxiety you calm them down and what
happens well the next day they want to
go out again well that's exactly what
happens to the Buddha so he's all
shorted out by his encounter with death
which is very little different than what
happens to Adam and Eve runs back
recovers for six-month he has
post-traumatic stress disorder he runs
home and he recovers for six months
right in time his anxiety lessened his
curiosity granny ventured outside again
this time the God sent a sick man into
view this creature he asked his
attendant shaking and palsy horribly
afflicted unbearable to behold a source
of pity and contempt what is he and the
attendant answered that's a man like
other men who was born whole but who
became ill and sick unable to cope a
burden to himself and others suffering
and incurable like other men you say
inquired the prince this could happen to
me and the attendant answer's no man is
exempt from the ravages of disease
once again the world collapse
got hammer returned to his home but the
delights of his previous life were ashes
in his mouth and he ventured forth a
third time the gods in their mercy sent
him a dead man in funeral procession
this creature he asked his attendant
laying so still appearing so fearsome
surrounded by grief and by sorrow
lost and forlorn what is he and the
attendant answered that is a man like
other man born of woman beloved and
hated who is once you who once was you
and now is the earth like other men you
say inquired the prince then this could
happen to me this is your end said the
attendant and the end of all men well
that's the end of childhood right
there's no going back after that it's
like Pinocchio goes back there's no one
home anymore it's there's nothing that
your father can do to protect you from
knowledge of death there's no returning
to the childhood unconsciousness because
you're new now no and there's no going
backwards suicide that's going backwards
that's how you replace your emergent
self-consciousness with the old blissful
unconsciousness and that's exactly what
suicidal people wish they're going to
destroy their painful self-consciousness
and make it all go away the world
collapsed a final time and Gautama asked
to be returned home but the attendant
had orders from the princes father and
took him instead to a festival of women
occurring near occurring nearby and a
grove in the woods the prince was met by
a beautiful assemblage who offered
themselves freely to him without
restraint in song dance and play in the
spirit of sensual love but Gautama could
think only of death and the inevitable
decomposition of beauty and took no
pleasure in the display well so you see
the parallels between one story and the
other they're the same they have the
same underlying structure initial
paradise partly childhood partly
unconsciousness the emergence of
knowledge of mortality into that and the
demolition of the of the paradise this
is the same meta story that we've been
talking about all along ordered state
collapse into chaos well the rest of the
story is the return like in the Bible
Bibles actually set up that
it's collapsed into history and then a
movement upward the question is what's
the movement upward that's the question
here when the collapse is caused by
knowledge of mortality and self caught
and the emergence of self-consciousness
and knowledge of death is there any
manner in which Redemption can be
attained or is that the final like is
that finally is that does that finally
demolish you well that's the question
and that's that's that's it's the answer
to that question that entire
civilizations constantly pursue and the
question is well what is the answer and
part of the answer is identification
with the spirit that generates order out
of chaos that's the answer it's
something like that and so then the
question is what does that mean well
that'll be what the last two lectures in
the course are about because we're down
to two last lectures so any questions
does it make sense more more importantly
really is there is there any way in
which it doesn't make sense because
these stories are not supposed to make
sense right that's the theory is that
their archaic superstitions or something
like that well it doesn't seem to me
that that's the case it seems to me that
they make insanely perfect sense they're
exactly right they tell you exactly what
human beings are like and exactly what
the situation that we face is so and so
then the question is well the diagnosis
is made properly what it has the cure
being properly identified well that's
what we'll discuss for the next two
sessions